Hello my name is Marshall Kirk McKusick
and I've been around as long as dinosaurs
and mainframes have ruled the world
which is to say the sixties and seventies
however by 1970s a new breed of mammals had begun to show up
on the scene
known as mini computers
although they were just toys in the 1970s they would soon grow
and take over most of the computing market
In 1970
at AT&T Bell laboratories two researchers Ken
Thompson and Dennis Ritchie began developing the
UNIX operating system
Ken Thompson who had been an alumnus at Berkeley
came back on a sabbatical in 1975 bringing UNIX
with him
In the year that he was there
he managed to get a number of graduate students interested
in UNIX
and by the time he left in 1976
Bill Joy has taken over in running the UNIX system
and in fact continuing to develop software for it.
Bill began packaging up the software that had
been developed under Berkeley UNIX and
and distributing it
as the Berkeley Software Distributions
whose name was quickly shortened to simply BSD
BSD continued to be distributed with
yearly distributions for almost fifteen
years
initially under Bill Joy and later under others including
yours truly.
By the late 1980s interest had began to grow
in freely redistributable software
so a number of us at Berkeley began separating
out
the AT&T proprietary bits of BSD
from those parts that were freely redistributable.
By the time of the final distribution at BSD
in 1992
the entire distribution was freely redistributable.
I live in a capsule history here
but if you're interested in the entire story
I have this three-and-an-half hour epic
which is available from my website www.mckusick.com
that gives the entire history of Berkeley.
Following the final distribution from Berkeley
two groups sprung up
to continue supporting BSD
the first of this was the NetBSD whose primary
goal was to support
as many different architectures as possible
everything from your microwave oven all way
upto your cray XMP
In fact today NetBSD supports nearly
sixty architectures.
The other group that sprang up was FreeBSD.
Their goal was to bring up BSD and support
as wide a set of devices as possible on the
PC architecture.
They also had a goal of trying to make the
system as easy to install as possible to
attract by a wide group of developers
I chose to work primarily with the FreeBSD
group
both doing software
and also together with George Neville Neil
writing this book ""The Design and Implementation
of the FreeBSD Operating System"".
Together with this book
I developed a course
which runs for twelve chapters
and thirty hours.
The purpose of this video
is to give you a taste
of that course.
What follows are excerpts from the first lecture
of the course
which of course you can also get from my website
www.mckusick.com.
Enjoy.
This class is nominally about FreeBSD
because well
that's what I know best and that's what
the textbook is organized around
but the fact of the matter is that it's really
a class about your UNIX and that
really covers sort of the broad range of things
in the open source arena as its FreeBSD
in Linux
which of course
you use a lot out
and
it also covers a commercial systems
%uh Solaris, HP-UX,
AIX and so on.
I am going to tend more towards the open
side
open source side of things.So it's really
going to be more FreeBSD in Linux than it's
going to be
Solaris and HP-UX and so on.
For the most part at the level of this course
we're dealing with the interfaces to the system
and
the fact that the matter is a those interfaces are highly
standardized at this point
and
whether it's FreeBSD or Linux or Solaris
or whatever
the Socket system call has to do the same
thing, it has to have the same arguments
in that,
it has to have the same effect
and so until you get down to the really nitty
details
of how they actually go about implementing
that
the differences are relatively minor.
So I would say that sixty to seventy percent
of the material that I'm covering
is just as true for FreeBSD as it would
be for Linux
or for Solaris
%uh AIX is a little bit
sort of off in the weeds
%uh as is HP-UX
but luckily we don't have to worry too much about
that.
Okay so
the other thing is that I'm going to assume that
all of you have used the system. I get
really sort of worried when people
you know raise the hands and ""Hey, what's a Shell?""
or I don't
put a lot of code up but a one piece of code and someone said ""Why
are there two pipe symbols in the middle of
that that If statement?"".
No we're not programming the Shell we're programming
in C.
So hopefully you can tell the difference between
Shell scripts and C code.
so okay but I am but am gonna assume
you haven't really looked inside the system.
So I gonna start everything to at a very
high level.
The problem is I have already discovered you come
from a lot of different sort of
backgrounds
and
levels of knowledge
and so
the way that I find works best to sort of
be useful to everybody is that three pass
algorithm
so what I will do is start the first pass a very
broad brush high level
description of what's going on
and then I will go back and I'll go through the
same material again but at a lower level of
detail
then I finally go back and go through a very nittily
low-level of detail
and the fact of this is if you are learning new stuff
as I'm doing the high-level thing
you are gonna be utterly washed by the time I get to
low level niggly details
but since I'm going to do it topic by topic
when I get to the end of one of those nearly
low level niggly details
I'll give you a clue as I will say ""Brain
reset, I'm starting a new topic"" so even if
you're completely lost
you can now start listening again plus I'm gonna get
the broad brush up again.
okay and for those of you that know a lot of
this stuff already
you'll probably find the broad brush rather boring
but by the time we get down to nearly low level
details I think you'll actually
pick up some things that you will find
useful and interesting.
So in this way hopefully everybody will
get some
useful percentage of material out of the course.
I am gonna start out by just
walking through and giving you the
outline of what we're going to try and do here
here
As I said we're going to go roughly
just about two-and-an-half hours of lecture
about two hours forty minutes
per week
and
so we will start off this week with an introduction.
This is as I said we're going to start from the
top
and then just start working our way down
so the general thing I'm going to do is
to talk about the interface
%uh which is something that you
are presumably fairly familiar with since
you've worked with that system
and then
you have to sort of layout terminology
although we use normal English words
they have
sometimes rather bizarre meanings compared to their
common usage
and
so I will just sort of lay out the terminology
lay out the
the way we talk about how the system is structured
and this week we will also talk about the
basic services ""What is it that the kernel is
providing for us?""
and then of course
we'll proceed to dive down in and and see how
that is done
so here in
Week number 2
we're gonna look at the system from the
perspective of
something that
manages processes.
One way of looking at the kernel is it's really
just a
the resource manager and the resource that
its managing are things going to do with processes
So we'll look at a process, what the structure of
it is
and
talk about the different ways that they can
be structured.
Process can for example be an address space
and can have one thread running in it can have
multiple threads running in it.
so we'll talk about the different ways
that we think a process is.
We will look at the management of those processes
we've got
to lay out the bits and pieces that
need to be managed
and then talk about
how we do that.
we'll talk about jails.. this is something
that you currently find only in FreeBSD
hasn't made it into
Linux yet although
the concept is being actively worked
on so my guess is that you'll see that
fairly soon.
we'll also then talk about scheduling
which is in essence how we decide what gets
to run, when it gets to run, how long it gets
to run, etc.
okay
The week after that we will go into virtual
memory.
Signals aren't really part of virtual memory
but they didn't fit into next week's
material so I just would dropped that at the
beginning
but the bulk of Week 3 is going to
be
the management of Virtual Memory. So we've got
a bunch of physical memory, a bunch of
processes that are
trying to use their address spaces
and we will talk about
essentially how you will make that all work
It's called a virtual memory because it's
sort of a cheat. We promise you the world and
then we deliver you
as small number of pages as we think we
can get away with.
Okay. So the first three weeks then essentially
get us through
looking at the world as if it was all
all about processes.
Then in Week 4 we change gears. we say
okay well you know
the kernel isn't just all about processes. You can sort of
look at it orthogonally and you can
say it's really just a giant I/O switch
it's just like a traffic cop that's just managing
these
I/O streams
and
so let's look at it from that perspective.
And
we'll start with special files, again this
sort of the interface when you talk about UNIX
systems, when you talk about
what's normally /dev
interface that gets you access
to the various I/O streams that are available
and we'll look at how that's organized and
the structure of it
which used to be fairly simple but in the
last decade has gotten
incredibly complicated.
We will also talk about pseudo terminals in
job control
this is about as interesting as watching the
grass grow but unfortunately it's
a major component of the system
and especially people that deal with system
administration have to know far more about
this than they probably ever thought they
wanted to.
Okay we will then continue in Week 5 with
the kernel I/O structure,
We will start with multiplexing of I/O. The
kernel of course has done this
always
but we're really talking more about how do
we export I/O multiplexing to
user applications.
We will then move into auto configuration strategy
Auto configuration
is what happens
typically or historically I guess you
could say as the system boots.
so all that stuff that comes out about
what
hardwares are on the machine and how it's all
interconnected
all of that is tied up in auto configuration
and that used to happen just once it boots
but in modern systems today
it's an ongoing process. It happens at boot
but it also happens
anytime you plug a new I/O device, a
PCMCIA card,
or you remove a disk or you put in a new disk.
or any sort of activity that changes the I/O
structure of the machine
auto configuration has to get fired back up
and figure out what's disappeared
and cleanup and figure out what new has arrived
to configure it in.
and then we'll talk
a little bit about the configuration of the
device driver
this actually gets into an area that
is
one well let me just give it as a bit
of advice to the class especially those of
you who work in system administration.
You really want to be careful that
you don't learn too much about device drivers
because there is really these three things that
it's not good to learn about and if you do
learn about it it's really good to keep it
to yourself
because if you become an expert or
viewed as an expert in any of these areas
you will become the designated stuccy for
that and your site you'll never get to do
anything
but that
so The three things that I highly
recommend not learning very much about are
device drivers,
send mail configuration files
or anything having to do
with LDAP or anything in
that general domain
because as I say
that will become your life's work
and
there's other things that you might find more interesting.
""Do you have a question?""
so one of my students empathizes with my point
I believe you said you worked on that mail
system
so you you might know something about
Sendmail configuration files but you don't
have to answer that
okay so we're going to talk about what a device
driver does and really just sort of the entry
points to it
but we're not going to talk about how you
write such a thing, how you debug such a thing
or much of anything about it. I actually used
to teach an entire class believe it or not
about device drivers
but then I realized the error of my ways and I have
since
gone through and made a point of forgetting
every slide in that talk.
okay so then we will move on to File system
and as always we'll start at the high level
talk about the interface what is it that is
exported out of the system
and then we will start diving down in the C and
how do we go about implementing that
so
we'll start with the
so called
Block I/O system
it's historically been called buffer
cache
and you still hear it called that periodically
and the fact of the matter is that there isn't really
about buffer cache anymore, there is just one big
cache in it.Its the VM cache
and the Filesystem has a view into it
and
the processes have a view into it but at
the end of the day
you really don't want the same information
on two different
pages of memory
because that just leads to trouble.
But Filesystems think they have buffers and so
there's this maneuver where we make
these things that look like what historically
were buffers
that really just map into VM system
but they're still managed in the way that
they have been
managed historically
okay We will then get down into Filesystem implementation
the local file system if you will
and into also
soft updates and snapshots.
this
for the time being is something that you see
only in FreeBSD
the alternative to soft updates is journalling
which is %uh more commonly used
for example what is used by ext3
and so I'll go through soft updates and
a lot of the issues in soft updates are the
same issues that you have to deal with journalling
what is it that we're protecting and how do we
go about doing that
and the difference is in the detail.
There is actually a paper in the back to your
notes if this is something that interests
you
it's a comparison of journalling versus
soft updates that was done
about five or eight years ago.
and not to spoil the punch line but the answers
they both work about are the same
Okay snapshots again is something that
if
you've worked with things like the network
appliance box you're probably quite
aware of what snapshots are and how they do
or don't work for you
this is the same functionality
in the Filesystem implemented in a
somewhat different way
okay so this
Week 6 is really going to be the local
file system
the disk connected to the machine
that we are dealing with.
Week 7 then we get into multiple
Filesystem support so how do we abstract out that
Filesystem layer
and support Multiple Filesystems at the
same time so for example in FreeBSD
you can of course run with their traditional
fast Filesystem
but if you happen to like the Linux Filesystem
better or you have to share a disk
with a Linux machine
you can run the ext2 or ext3
and it will perfectly happily do that
so
we will have to look then at how do we provide
interface so that we can plug in all these different
Filesystems that we want to support
another area of which there's been a great
deal of growth at least in code complexity
is so-called Volume Management
so in the
good old days a Filesystem lived on a disk or
piece of disk and that was that
but in this day and age
that won't do any more so we aggregate disks
together by striping them or RAID
arraying them
or various other things
and we need a whole layer in the system just to
manage those disks
we'll then get to the as an example of an alternative
Filesystem we're going to talk about the
Network Filesystem or NFS
but that's not because this is
the world's best remote file system
or the cleanest design or any of the
properties you might hope that
such a class as this one would have
but it's ubiquitous
very widely used
and
so we're going to talk about that one
okay we'll
then once again switch gears in Week 8
and turn our attention to of Networking and
Interprocess communication
and
again we'll start from the very top so we'll
go through, we'll go with concepts, the terminology
that gets used
and what's the difference between domain
based addressing and an address domain you know
we'll go through
what the basic IPC services are,
essentially what are all the system calls that
have anything to do with networking
and
just sort of describe what each of them are
and I'm going to go through
a somewhat contrived example
that makes use of every one of those interfaces
and just to sort of show how they all connect
together
and for those of you that work
in networking or had done any kind of network
programming
if you're looking for a week to miss and the
Week 8 is the one to miss that's 'cause that's
the sort of most basic
lecture that I'm going to give
If you are not sure whether or not you need to
go through that, there is
one of the papers in the back
it is an introduction to Interprocess communication
read that paper if you say yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah you are done with Week 8.
on the other hand if you don't come to Week
and then in Week 9 I say
I call on you and say alright what is it
that listen system call does and you
can't tell me
you're gonna get a demerit
okay
then in Week 9 we will get into the actual
networking implementation itself, we go
through system layers as we did
in all the other areas
and
we will spend a significant portion of that
class talking about routing
routing
for those of you that haven't had the pleasure
of dealing with it
is a black art
or at least a dark science
and
so
we'll talk about it
from the perspective first of all of what
do we do locally within the machine
and then what are some of the bigger strategies
that we can use for doing routing
enterprise
wide routing or
area wide routing something like throughout the
state of California or throughout the US whatever
this again like device drivers is really
just sort of a nickel
tour through the
what the choices are what that the basic
strategies are that are used
If you're thinking you're going to walk out
of here
knowing how to set up a routing well sorry
we are not going to get that far
but you should at least have a pretty good idea
of what the issues are
and what the general solutions are
okay then finally in Week 10 well not finally
but next few weeks and
we will go through the Internet Protocols
primarily TCP/IP
and this is
what are the algorithms that are used
and I'm putting a particular emphasis
for this particular class
on
changes that have been made in the protocols
to deal with a lot of the sort of attacks that
we've been seeing the SYN attacks and
that sort of thing
rather than just a straight
iteration of what the actual protocols
are
I'll talk primarily about IPv4
but I will also try and talk a bit about
IPv6 as well
all right so the first ten weeks are
sort of the kernel course
now we attack two weeks at the end
to talk about
sort of the bigger picture of
System Tuning,Crash dump analysis that level of
thing
The idea is to really consolidate what
we figured out or talked about in the first
ten weeks and
how that applies to tools that we have available
to us to
look at what the system is doing,
analyze what the system is doing
and hopefully
improve
the performance of what the system is doing
and
for the most part the kind of tuning that I'm
talking about is not
going in and hack hack hacking your kernel
because the fact that the matter is
most of the time you can't do that anyway
so it's more looking at it from the perspective
of saying
is this system running badly because it doesn't
have enough memory on it?
or is it running badly because there isn't enough
I/O capacity?
or is it running badly because it's got
enough I/O capacity but
certain drives are being overloaded
or is it
being overrun because we're simply trying
to do too much on this machine? etc.
so that's the sort of level of thing that we're
looking at it
but tied into
lot of concepts that we talked before so we can talk
about active virtual memory
and what that means
and
essentially measure what it is and hopefully
then you will understand in the context of what
we talked about in the VM section
what that really means
the Crash dump analysis is one of these
topics that
you are gonna love or hate
you actually have to deal with crashed
dumps
its people find it invaluable
and if you don't have to deal with Crash dumps
it's an incredible mass of boring detail
the only good part of it is that that's the
whole session is only about an hour long
If it interests you, listen closely
and if it bores you, well, its only an hour long
okay lastly we'll talk a little bit about
security issues
again this is really more to the tools that
are available
to deal with security staff as opposed to a
complete tutorial on
how to implement security so those of you
that deal with security
this is just gonna to be sort of security one oh
one
for those of you
that have but
you'll have to deal with it but haven't really
thought about it
it'll probably scare you to death and
you wonder how to keep the machines from
being hijacked everyday
Okay so that's in essence what we're going
to try and do here
anybody have any comments, questions, thoughts.
No? All right well.
Let's get started
we will be begin on page fifteen with an
overview of the kernel.
Hopefully nobody's lost yet.
What's a kernel? All right.
so starting at the very top
the big broad brush
what we have is
a UNIX virtual machine and
virtual machines are actually something
that has been around
as a concept since the sixties
difference is really just sort of the level
of the interface that people have dealt with
when they talk about Virtual Machines
in the 1960s
computers were these enormous things you would
have
your computer room would be something that'd be
three times the size of this conference
room if you had
a computer
the computer itself was
tall as a refrigerator freezer
imagine
five or eight or ten of these units
side by side that itself made up the computer
that would be one big
for the core processor and the one which
should be the floating point unit and several
of them that would be the memory the core memory
literally the core memory
and then they'd be other rows of these
disk drives which were about the size of the washing
machine
and then behind that since you couldn't store
everything on disks so
then you had rows of tape drives
and then you had this little
set of sort of
munchkins that would run around and and tend
to the machine and they'd mount tapes and take
off tapes and mount disc packs and remove disc packs
because
the drives themselves were very expensive and
so
you wouldn't just as today we have a
one spindle that was dedicated just to one set
of platters
you could take out a
set of platters and put in another
hundred megabytes set of platters and these are
platters that are
this big around and it's like six or eight
of them and
giant head assemblies they comes rumbling in and
out
anyway one of these giant giant machines
that costs many millions of dollars would run
at about ten
million instructions per second, 10 mips
and 10 mips
was more computing power than anybody
could possibly imagine using in a single application
just
by contrast you know this
four-year-old laptop here is probably on
the order of
one or two hundred mips
but anyway
people couldn't really view what we would
do with a lot of computing power
and the other thing was that you didn't have
a notion of sort of an operating system that had
applications running on it
because
everybody wanted to write straight to
the raw hardware
and so
what IBM who was a big manufacturer
of machines in those days
did what they came up with this thing called
the VM
and this was a little
you'd call an operating system really
but what it did is it cloned
independent copies of the machine that worked just
like the original machines so you could boot
something that you thought it was an operating
system
on top of VM
so you take one least ten mip machines and
it would clone
six identical one mip copies
and then you could boot
whatever you wanted on each one of those machines
so
if you were doing database stuff you would boot your
database because database cannot ran on the raw hardware
or if you're doing payroll who would boot up the payroll
program
or if you actually tried to service
users you could boot a time sharing batch thing
that would read card images and print
stuff out
or they even had TSO the Time Sharing
Option where you could interactively sit
and type and send
stuffs in and get answers back
and
also you could boot TSO so whatever set
of
things you need you could boot them and they ran
independently as if they were running on their
own machine
but all the VM did was it give you an exact
raw copy of the hardware
so when UNIX came along
they sort of liked the notion of
providing the concept of independent
things that you could operate in
but they wanted it at a higher level
so you're looking really to do it
instead of at the raw hardware level
to do it at a process level
and the idea that then was that the interface you
would program to would be what we think of as
a System call interface today
and the idea then was that
you would be given a process or set of processes
and those were independent. your process
couldn't affect
the address space of another processor. You couldn't reach
over and mess around with their addresses,
you couldn't mess around with their I/O
channels
you could slow them down by
being a pig but
that was about the only way that you could affect
other processes
and
so
what the interfaces that they had there
was one that had these characteristics
had a paged virtual address space
so you didn't have to know as in the old days how much physical
memory is on the machine and make your application
fit into that amount of memory
you just had what looked like a large
uniform address space even if the underlying
hardware had segments or some other
hardware brain damage
it looked to you like he just had a big uniform
address space and
the size of your address space was independent
of the amount of memory that was on your machine
your address space couldn't be bigger than amount of
physical memory
cause we sort of move pages around underneath
whatever part address space was actually
active
and there's obviously limits to this if
you are trying to run a 1 gigabyte of
application on top of
ten megabytes of memory
it's probably going to bring new meaning to
same day service
but if you're willing to wait long enough it
will eventually move the pages around and you will
progress through getting your application run
another thing was dealing with software
interrupts
in the old days
you had to understand how the hardware worked
in order to deal with exceptional conditions
so for example if you did a divide by zero
the hardware would jump through some
vector location or
something
and you had know how that worked and make
sure that you had your program
usually some little bit of assembly language
set up to deal with that
and UNIX said let's let's get away
from the hardware here
and so they did this thing called signals
and so they just define a set of the signals is that
if you do divide by zero
you simply register a routine you
want to have called you don't have to know
how the hardware figured it out
you just know that that routine is going to get
called and you can deal with it at that point
well we got set of timers and counters to keep
track of what we're doing, this is really more
for counting than anything else but
applications may want to have access to that.
we have a set of identifiers that we're
going to use for things like accounting,
protection and scheduling and so on
and one of the
the early philosophies of UNIX was to try
and keep it simple.
operating systems have gotten very baroque
in particular the thing that
pre dated UNIX was a thing called
Multix
Multix was was a joint project between
Honeywell, a big computer manufacturer of the
time
AT&T bell laboratories
the big industrial laboratory at that time
and MIT
a big university then and
still today
and those three organizations got
together to try and build this
time sharing operating system
and it
it just got bigger and
more grandiose and more complex and never
finished
because as soon as they sort of see
oh we know how to do that but we could
do this other thing too and so then they would tear it
apart and
they never really got to something that
could be put into production
and so the
AT&T
Bell laboratories decided to pull out of
that project
and
the two of the people that had been working on
that project, Ken Thompson and Dennis Richie
were sort of bummed because they were now
back to typing cards and putting them through
card readers and
they had gotten used to the idea that you could
actually
sit at an ASSR33 teletype and interact
with your computer
and so
they found an old %uh PDP-8 sitting off in
the corner that had been abandoned
and started working on this little tiny operating
system which they called UNIX
which eventually moved to the PDP-11 and
became what we have today
but because it was
they were coming first of all from Multix
where everything had been done and
in great grandiose detail
and because they're fundamentally were two
of them working on it and they wanted to get something
done and
within a year or so
one of their philosophies was
let's find the one way of doing things
let's not have eight ways from Sunday let's just
get the one way
and that's what we will provide. So what is
the sort of core set of things that we need.
well first thing is when it comes to identifiers,
let's not have you know
eighty thousand different identifiers
so they came up with process identifiers,
user identifier and at that time a single group
identifier and later expanded
and they used that sort of identifiers for everything
so its used for counting, used for making
protection decisions, used for scheduling
decisions
and
again it was the simplicity of thing which
was what was driving their decision
but they're really sort of two key ideas
that they had
that really made the difference that
that's what set them up side
from what everybody else had done before them
and which
in retrospect is something that has been pervasive
more or less ever since
the first of these was the notion
that we have a unique descriptor space
that is
given a descriptor it can reference
any I/O device
so or even any kind of I/O channel
so you can have a descriptor for terminal
or descriptor for a file or descriptive for
a disk or descriptor for a pipe or descriptor
for a socket
and
you don't need to know
what it references in order to be able to read
and write that thing
so if I hand you a descriptor
you can read from that the descriptor or you can write
to that descriptor
and
the correct thing will happen
and you'd say well
that's so obvious I mean how else could you
possibly think of doing it?
well predating UNIX
everything was done with
a little subsystem
that would open a file, read a file, write a
file, close a file
and there was another set of system calls which
would open a terminal, read a terminal, write terminal,
close terminal
and yet another one
which was create a pipe, read a pipe,
write a pipe and so on.
so if you are just a drop dead stupid
program like say CAD
you would have to have code in there and say was
my input a terminal which in case I need to
use the read terminal
or is it a file which in case I need
to use read file or is it a pipe in which in case
I need to use read pipe
and so the program itself had to have all
this
coding in it
whereas when they went to
the uniform descriptor space
CAD doesn't know it doesn't need to know
it just says
read my input,
write the output
and it works and we add a new type of descriptor
and
CAD just continues to work just as it always
did.
So this proved to be a very powerful construct
and pretty much every operating system after
UNIX
did that there's
one exception of %uh
large company in the Pacific North-West
that still has not quite uniform descriptor
space
but %uh that's part of their legacy that really
they're working on that.
Longhorn will be here.
and anyway
this set of facilities then
makes up the UNIX virtual machine
and
in some sense we still see virtual machines
being used today in fact we're seeing sort
of a reversion
back to some of the IBM stuff in things
like the VMware
which is
essentially allow you to go back to booting
native operating systems again so sort of
interesting to watch
that the sort of
pendulum of back going back and forth
of what's the correct layer
for for doing
virtual machines
Okay? so far so good?
all right so I said that there were
two key ideas that UNIX had
the first of these being the uniform descriptor
space
the second one which was really critical was
this notion of processes as a commodity
item
so here on Page 17 I've tried to lay
it out
the
that the components that make up a process
and
what do I really mean when I say a process as
a commodity item
okay leading up to
UNIX
the systems that pre-dated it,
processes were these very large
heavyweight expensive things
and
if you look at
MVS which was the operating system
that ran on IBM for doing multiple processing
and
the system administrator would decide at boot
time
what degree of multiprocessing they wish
to support
so they'd say well
well, we'll let upto six things happen at once
and so as part of booting up
they would create six
processes
and now you as a user if you wanted to do
something let's say you wanted to
compile and run a program
you would be given a process
and it was up to you
to figure out how to stage what you needed
done
and
that this was often fairly complex
and so you would have to write out all the
steps that you wanted
in this wonderful thing called JCL
Job Control Language.
Job Control Language was send mail configuration
file of the sixties
there where people whose sole job at the company
was how to put this stuff together 'cause
all you had to do is get one extra space or
a missing comma
something in there
and the whole thing would just blow up. it would
just sort of spit the card deck back at
you and say well
somewhere in there is a mistake that's sort of
in the general area of this card
and I can't deal with it. Fix it.
and of course
in those days it wasn't just a matter of hitting
carriage when you know make carriage return you have to
get your deck pull out the card, and type the
new one, put it back in and re-submit it
As heaven forbid you couldn't touch that
card reader you know, it had to be done by
an operator
so the card deck will read through it would
disappear and
you know if you're lucky a few minutes later
if you were not lucky a few hours later
you would get
a print out
which was what had happened and then you could
look at it and you know
I put a comma in the wrong place I guess
I get to do it all again
so
the thing you would need to do there for compiling and running a program
was you'd have to break into these steps. well
I need to run the preprocessor
and so clean out whatever gump that was left
over on that process from the previous user
put the preprocessor in there
and then read from this file here let's
say I gotta put it somewhere so creative
scratch file over on this disk and
it was excruciating detail like how many cylinders
and how many tracks and this and that
blocks blah blah blah
and don't forget any of those parameters 'cause
it'll spit it out if you do
and so then it would run the first step in that
if its successful then you'd have sitting
in this scratch file that you had created
the output of the preprocessor and then
you'd load the first pass of the compiler
and you say now read from that scratch file
and create this other scratch file over here and
when thats successful and we need to delete that
one
and then load the second pass, put that back
into another scratch file and then we run this
assembler, and the optimizer then the
loader this and that
finally run the program
and if all goes well
you know at step sixteen out comes the answer
forty two. so UNIX
said, look this is silly
a lot of this is just
bookkeeping
and computers do bookkeeping really well
and you'll recall yeah but it's going to take
all these cycles it's like
computers are supposed to be labor-saving
devices right? so
they came up with this notion that they would
create processes on the fly as needed
you had
you've had a preprocessor in two
steps of the compiler and then
optimizer and then a loader
we just create Boom seven processes
and we connect them together with pipes
and so we take the input and you know run
through in
through the pipes and you know out the end
you get the the
executable
and
we will simply create each of these processes
so you as a user just
type you know the C compiler and it just
fork these things pipe them together got the result
and
then once it was done with this processes is
just threw them away so any time you'd create a
new process and it came to you pristine clean
and you needed a bunch of things it did
put everything in intermediate files
the fact of the matter is in the early days
those computers
didn't really have enough memory to support
all that stuff at once so
behind you those pipes were actually implemented
as files
but you didn't have at least to remember to create
them and delete them
and deal with them
as far as you were concerned it just look stuff
flowing through pipes and of course today it
just
does flow through pipes in memory
okay so
this notion then that that we're just gonna
create processes on the fly is needed and
connect them together as needed
it was a novel concept
and it wasn't that somehow mysteriously figured
out how to create processes cheaply
cause they hadn't
they were still
really expensive to create
but that extra effort
was
worth it because it was saving a lot of programming
time
so my favorite example is you run ls
so we have to create a process
load the ls binary into it
it prints a line or two on your screen
and we tear the entire thing down and return
all its resources back to the system
more than ninety percent of the cost of running
ls is creating and destroying the process
a tiny fraction of it is actually running
ls
but it goes so fast, who cares right
so the point is that
that concept of just creating things as
needed
again was very powerful
and is one that is just pervasive today
okay so what is a process actually made up
of
it gets some amount of CPU time or at
least we do dearly hope that it gets some
amount of CPU time, the lack of getting
CPU time
that makes it
a computer so sluggish
of course
others really boils down to scheduling
and we're going to talk about scheduling
probably more than you care to
in a couple weeks time
we have the asynchronous events
these are the external events that
are coming in
so
they may be either things that
were coming in from the outside world like
start, stop and quit
oh
out-of-band data arrival notification that kind
of thing
or it may in fact be things that the program
is bringing down upon itself
such as a segment fault, a divide by zero
and some other
what would normally be viewed as incorrect
operation
and so we'll talk about that when we talk about
signals
every program
gets some amount of memory
it gets an initial amount when it starts
up injured generally allocates more as it
goes along
this of course we will deal with very extensively
will spend an entire week on it
when we talk about how virtual memory is implemented
and
then we get I/O descriptors
I used to say that every program had to have
at least one I/O descriptor since
it absolutely had no input
absolutely no output
then it was sort of pointless
of course I had to have one of my students
come up and point out to me there is an a
class of programs
which don't need I/O descriptors
and that is
these things called benchmarks
it just compute something all we really care
about is how long it takes them to compute
we don't actually care what the answer is
In theory we don't
I personally like my benchmark stop with
something so I can see it there
doing computing the right thing
but in theory
that wouldn't be necessary
outside of that class of programs
everything needs some sort of descriptors and
of course we'll talk about descriptors
quite extensively
as we go through the I/O subsystem
okay so the executive summary is that processes
are
the fundamental service that is provided by
UNIX
and
what we're going to spend essentially the
next two and a half weeks working on
is
what what makes up processes
we'll go into much more detail about each of these
four points
and
then how do we actually go about
providing that
bit of service
the next thing that I'm
going to do now is this go through and lay
out some of the terminology that
we have when
we're talking about processes
so this is sort of the big picture here were
on page eighteen
and
you can see we have sort of three bits that
make up
the system
we have the currently running user process
and then what we call the top half of the kernel
and the bottom half of the kernel
now this would be a picture for a uniprocessor
so one CPU
if we had a multiprocessor
%uh then we would have
one instance of the kernel
but multiple instances of the user process
but for any given CPU on a multiprocessor
it is running exactly one process
so you may think they we're running for four-five
processes all at once
but the fact of the matter is that any instant
in time there's only one process which is
actually running
and
that is the one that we have loaded in the system
now we give the illusion that were running
lots of things because we switch between them
rather quickly
so it looks like things are happening in all
windows at once
but in reality
that's not really happening
okay so there is a set of properties that I want to
look at
that had to do with each one of these parts here
but just to sort of look at it from the
big picture perspective
what you see here
is
there is boundary between the user process
and the top half of the kernel
which is really just like a glorified sovereignty
call
it's a lot like calling into a library routine
like calling strcat, strcpy or something
like that
when you do a system call
we take that same set of parameters
now this is sort of
brick Wall here if you will
that is protecting
the top half of the kernel
from the application
I'll go more into some detail about how that
actually gets implemented
but in essence you can think of it
is is there sort of this whaling Wall and these little
chinks there and you can sort of push a request
through
and somebody other sides sort of pulls that
looks at it and decides whether they're going
to
dain to provide service to you
and if they do then they sort of send it back
well like a library where you can just sort
of reach in and walk around if you want to
you
good programming practices you don't do that
but
you could
all right so
the the top half of the kernel is really looks
a lot like
a big library
%uh it just happens to be a library
routines
that deal with things where processes need
to interact with each other
in fact for many people they don't understand
for what's the difference between the C
library and the top half of the kernel
if it's something that you're doing that
no other process needs to know about
then it can be in the C library
so if you call strcat to concatenate two
strings together
nobody else needs to know you're doing that
you don't need to coordinate with anybody
else that you're doing that
it's just happening
so that goes in the C library.
on the other hand if you're reading or writing
the file
there may be other processes that are also
reading and writing that file
and therefore that
has to be done by the kernel
because they can coordinate
all the different processes that are trying to access
that file.
so the top half of the kernel is pretty straightforward
code
it looks a lot like any other library that
you would write if you look at top half kernel
code you know you see all read, come in
it's got these parameters we Mark around we
get some data that we put it in the buffer and
we return back
and in fact writing code for the top half of
the kernel is
not all that difficult to do
it's
you have
for many of the same properties that you would
when you're writing user level application
code
the bottom half of the kernel is where things
start to get nasty
because the bottom half of the kernel is the part
of the system
that deals with all of the asynchronous events
in the system
is things like device drivers,
timers
that level of thing
that are driven by hardware events
so
for example a packet arrives on the network
that causes an interrupt to come and
that will be handled by the bottom half of
the kernel
and historically
when an interrupt came in it preempted whatever
else was going on
and it ran until it finished and then it returned
and it could not
go to sleep to wait for resources or other
things
%uh in current systems
you can actually go to sleep in the interrupt driver
and waiting for
some other activity to complete
it is however
not a good idea to do that
because
the usual case of most device drivers is they
can finish whatever they're doing in an interrupt
without ever blocking
and so
when an interrupt comes in we assume that you're
not going to sleep
and if you actually
then go to sleep.oh man
you didn't tell us you're going to do this we
have to go off to do a whole lot of other work
that we had originally planned on doing
so if you go to sleep in a device driver
you are taking a very serious performance hit
so it's highly recommended that you don't
do that
but if you have to you can
on it's because of this historic behavior
or
of not being able to sleep in the bottom half
of the kernel
that you have certain properties that have
taken over in device drivers
and that is
that a device driver should be handed all
the resources it needs to get his job done
you don't give a disk device driver
Go read this
and put it somewhere
you have to say
Go read this particular block
here is a chunk of memory that I want that
data to put in
and
notify me when it's done
because
things like allocating memory are classic
places where you end up having to go to sleep
to wait for stuff to happen
and
historically you couldn't do that
even currently don't want to have to do that
so device drivers generally have all
resources pre allocated
and then they can just go
the one place where this doesn't work
is the network
and in particular
you don't know when somebody's going to send
packets to you
you say well you're looking to open connections
but if you're doing something like IP forwarding
there's no
top half state it's dealing with this packets
they're just coming in on one interface being
sent out on another interface
they never pass through any part of the top
half of the kernel
and so in the case of network device drivers
they need to allocate memory
and
if memory gets into short supply
and they try to allocate memory and it's not
available
they historically couldn't wait for memory to be
and even in practice today don't wait
for memory to become available
they simply drop the packet on the floor
it's like well I didn't have any place to
put it sorry oops
now that doesn't cause incorrect behavior
because the higher level protocols will retransmit
but it does cause great performance problems
because retransmission means that connections
stall
they have to back up
they have to resend data
and so on
so you really want to avoid dropping packets
if you can possibly help it
and consequently
we tend to
pre allocate a certain amount of memory for
the network drivers
and
we try very hard to make sure that we're not
going to run out of memory but
if packets come fast enough and we can't deal
with them
as quickly as they are arriving then over short period
of time
we get to the point where we simply have to start
dropping packets
okay this is a part of kernel that you do not wish to
write code for
because it is extremely difficult to
debug
you get these bugs where
the only time it happens is on the third Tuesday
when there's a full moon
and
we have a disk interrupt followed by %uh a
terminal character coming in
and the network packet arriving of size fifteen
twenty two
and when all those things happened
the system panics
and of course there's like it panics
cause you're following some bad pointer
something that should have been there
but was freed some time in the distant past
we are not sure when
and
try to debug things like that is extremely
difficult
and you can
think well I think I found the problem but
it's not reproduceable
you know you have to wait for the next third
Tuesday with a full moon and blah blah blah
to happen
and
you know so you sort of statistically
guess that you fix that you know I was getting
this bug once every three days
and now it's gone for two weeks without happening
did you fix that?
or if you've been lucky
and and it's
that coupled with the fact that you're
dealing with hardware
and hardware rarely works the way it's documented
to work
and so you know they're doing everything that
it says you're supposed to do
it still doesn't work because you didn't set
the fiddle bit over on that other place over
there
that's not documented anywhere but if it's
not said it doesn't work
occasionally
so this is another reason that you really want
of avoid
dealing with this part of the system if
you can possibly help
okay but lets go through and and look at some
of the properties here starting up at
the user process
we're running with
preemptive scheduling
now there's several caveats here
preemptive scheduling is the default
so called shared scheduler
that is what you normally use there are other
schedulers like the real time scheduler
where what I'm saying isn't that true
we'll talk about some of the schedulers was
later
but the usual scheduler that you're running
on under UNIX is a shared scheduler
and under the shared scheduler user applications
run with pre emptive scheduling
and pre emptive scheduling means that
you run at the whim of the system
if it wants you to run
you run
once you to start running you have no guarantee
of how long you're going to run
it might like to run for three instructions
and then decide it doesn't like you many more
it wants to run something else
or you might get to run for several seconds
and in a row with the with no intervening
things interrupting you
you just don't know
and
really all you know is
that
they claim that they're using statistics
and that and that the statistics are fair
and so on average you're going to get a reasonable
amount of time but thats
up to the system you don't control that
the real point here
is that you don't have any way of creating
a critical section
you can't say okay I don't want to be interrupted
during this particular sequence of things
so you have to program
assuming that you may be interrupted at any
point
okay
the next thing is that when you're running
in a user process
you are running in
with the processor in what's called unprivileged
mode
one of the requirements for running any kind
of a UNIX system
is that you have to have a processor that
support privileged and unprivileged
two different modes of operation
in privileged mode which is what the kernel
runs in
the entire repertoire
of the hardware is available
by this I mean you can set all the registers
you can fiddle with the memory management
unit you can initiate I/O
you can access any memory anywhere
etc
when you're running in unprivileged
mode which is what user processes run in and
this a large subset of the instructions which
you cannot execute
you cannot initiate I/O on
devices
you cannot change the memory mapping
you cannot access memory that's not part of
your address space
you cannot execute certain instructions
like halt
and
so in general you are protected
from manipulating anything that's outside of your
address space
this of course is desirable because
when you're running in this unprivileged
mode
you're protected
from other processes manipulating you
and they're protected from you manipulating
them
for those of you that have had that misfortune
to have to use
early versions of windows up to about ninety
eight
they always ran with the processor
running in privileged mode
even in applications
and so either maliciously or accidentally
you could stop on other people address space
or you could stop on the kernel
and a lot of the blue screen of death was
people just
following wild pointers and trashing different
parts of the system
taking everything down
it also makes it
far easier to
implement things like viruses and worms and
other things because
a user application can we rewrite the boot
block on the disk they can just the write down
and manipulate the registers that allow them
to do whatever they want
whereas when you're running in unprivileged
mode you can't write those kinds of
of things
so modern versions of Windows anything from about
2000 on
now run with privileged and unprivileged mode
but UNIX has always required that
and so when you're running an
user process
you cannot block I mean
you cannot execute the instructions which
cause a context switching to occur
you can't pick what's going to run next
you can't make that thing run next all you can
do
is go to the operating system and say
hey I've got nothing to do. pick somebody else
to run
and the operating system is the think they can
then execute the instructions which cause
a different process to be loaded
and run
alright.finally while you're in a user application you're
running on a user stack
that's part of the user's address space
so
part of creating a process gives you a runtime
stack
as part of a virtual address space and so it
can be
more or less up to the limits of the hardware
as big as you want it to be
so if you are running on thirty two-bit processor
you're stack can get the 2 gigabytes
and
the what this means is that anytime you
allocate local variables
you don't have to worry about Oh
is that gonna overrun my stack?
so if you need
a hundred thousand double precision floating
point numbers
you can just as a local variable allocate
an array of size a hundred-thousand type
double
and it just decrements your stack pointer by
hundred hundred thousand bytes
away you go
it's just virtual address space
as you'll see when we get into the kernel
that ceases to be the case